<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pitifull estate of the time present A Christian consideration of the miseries of this time, with an exhortation to amendement of life: compiled by one zealous in the lawe of God, and set forth by publike autority, being perused and allowed by the same.</title>
            <author>I. S., fl. 1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1564</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21504</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847388</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847388</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11244)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1583:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pitifull estate of the time present A Christian consideration of the miseries of this time, with an exhortation to amendement of life: compiled by one zealous in the lawe of God, and set forth by publike autority, being perused and allowed by the same.</title>
                  <author>I. S., fl. 1564.</author>
                  <author>Stubbes, John, 1543-1591, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Whitecrosse strete, by Henry Denham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Anno Domini 1564]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Stubbs.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:1"/>
            <p>The Pitifull eſtate of the Time preſent.</p>
            <p>A Chriſtian conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the miſeries of this time, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life: compiled by one zealous in the <hi>Lawe of God,</hi> And ſet forthe by Publike Autority, being peruſed and allowed by the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> 6.</bibl>
               <p>Giue eare yee that rule the multitudes, for power is giuen you of the Lord, &amp; ſtrength from the higheſt, which ſhall trye youre workes and ſearche oute your ymaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, howe that yee being Officers of hys Kingdome haue not executed true Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherefore ye ſhall haue the ſorer pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Whitecroſſe ſtrete, by Henry Denham.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S ACCORDING</hi> to the ſaying of Saint Paul,
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> all that is written is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our inſtruction and learning, that wee might faſhion oure ſelues to the good wyll and pleaſure of GOD, in follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of vertue and embracing that is good, forſaking vice and deteſting that which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. I therefore hereby moued and occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, did peruſe of late a booke of ſmall volume which hath to name, the Triall of truthe, ſet forth a yeare paſſed and more, in the which booke, as the Auctor zealouſlie made a briefe diſcourſe of the ſundrie viſitations and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God for our forgetfulneſſe of him tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe our ſinfull wickedneſſe, ſo did he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe brotherly warne &amp; admoniſhe vs to leaue, forſake, and abhorre our accuſtomed euill, and Chriſtianlike exhorte vs to liue in newneſſe of lyfe, putting vs in remembraunce that the Fier which fell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, ſo quickely defacing the buge Temple of Paules, the ſtraunge and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſhape as well of Children as of beaſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:3"/>(wherof there were diuers and ſundrye,) with alſo the vnſeaſonable time then thorow the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dropping ſhowers, were altogither plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and tokens of Gods vengeaunce and heauy wrath to come vpon vs and more ſharply to punniſhe vs than euer he did before, where of we might aſſure our ſelues, vnleſſe with hearty repentaunce and ſpecty amendment of our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked life wee tourned vnto the Lorde our God. And this in maner was the effect of that little worke, wherein it appeareth that the Auctor was more carefull for vs than wee are for oure ſelues. For notwithſtanding that he, with alſo many others, haue not ceaſſed thorow their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual, daily and painefull trauaile in writing and ſetting forth of Godly Bookes, wherof neuer ſince Christes time more plentye than of late yeres hath bene, teaching, inſtructing, perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, exhorting, admoniſhing, and in Goddes behalfe threatening vs, &amp; by all meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeeking to drawe vs from euill to good, from worſe to better, from ſinne to godly lyfe, that we might learne to do the wil of our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: yet are wee for all this ſo vnmindefull of GOD and of his good gifts in his creatures, and our mindes ſo ſet and buſied in the vaine and tranſitory things of this worlde, that wee
<pb facs="tcp:12421:3"/>are not at layſure to know God, nor by hearing and reading to learne how to attayne vnto the world that is permanent and euerlasting: but eyther the workes ſo ſet forth for our instructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſo long that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not intend to reade them thorow (although in the meane we bee neyther idle nor yet wel occupied) or elſe if they be ſhort, then ſoner red ouer than wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as the crooked conditions and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of vs wretched people of England, doth to euidently declare, whoſe abhominations are ſo vile &amp; detestable in the ſight of God, as that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but maruell how either wee dare preſume to aske or hope to haue any thing at the hands of our Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Father, that might be benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or neceſſary for vs, but rather loke for preſent destruction, &amp; to be roted from the face of the Earth, nothing regarding the many and often warnings of God by his ministers, neither yet his louing correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which with fauor hitherto we haue had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alas how oft hath he called vs ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſo carefully, ſo louingly, ſo fatherly, tendering vs euen as the Father his children, &amp; yet we will not come but ſtill ſo muche neglect his mercifull goodnes, that nedes he muſt of his iuſtice, being a gelous god that hath pmiſed to viſit the ſins of the fathers vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the children, vnto the thirde &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:12421:4"/>fourth generation of them that hate him, euen punniſh with ſorrowe to vs our ſinnes, and laye vppon vs the heauie burthens that oure wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes hath worthilye deſerued, for where the ſhaking of the rodde will not helpe or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, there muſt needes ſharpe ſtrokes followe, and wee ſhall haue them, let vs aſſure our ſelues thereof, except ſpedie amendement of our wicked life and carneſt reformation of our mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous manners, which as I heartilye wiſhe, and bicauſe I woulde (as much as in mee is) be a meanes to prouoke and ſtirre vp my brethren thereto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (whoſe forgetfulneſſe of their duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes God I heartelye lamente and bewaile) haue therefore thought it my part, though with eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnacquainted by pleaſantneſſe of ſtile to pleaſe the Reader, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this ſimple ſorte plainely to declare my good will, tendering (as nature forceth mee) the welfare of the whole body of this Realme of Englande, whereof although I be but a weake, yet thorowe the grace of God, a well willing member.</p>
            <closer>Reade and diſcerne.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:4"/>
            <head>The Pitifull eſtate of the Tyme preſent.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H WRETCHED AND</hi> graceleſſe people, why do we ſo long tempt the Lord our God, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row our diuelliſh doin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges deny him? we deny him I ſaye in that wee beeing a people voyd of all Godly ſeare, ſtill continue careleſſe and neglecte the keeping of the holy preceptes and commaundements of our eternall and euerliuing GOD, whome we thorow the leudneſſe of our lyfe do ſo ſhamfully abuſe and offende. For (alas) how doth all kinde of vice ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increaſe than diminiſh?
<note place="margin">Vice flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth in England.</note> For who heareth not the horrible vice of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and ſwearing ſo brimme and rife in the mouth of young and olde of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees as well in courte as in countrey,
<note place="margin">Otheo co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in olde and yonge.</note> that almoſt euery toung is embrued w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloudy othes, which though it highly offend the Maieſty of God, and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerueth ſharpe correction and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:5"/>yet not all ſo conſidered, but euery one ſtill ſuffered to ſweare and forſweare, ſincking in their ſinne.</p>
            <p>Filthy whoredome likewiſe,
<note place="margin">The whor dome of Englande ſtinketh be fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of God.</note> which in all degrees and places, as it is to bee hated as moſt ſhamefull in the ſight of the Almightie, ſo would God that hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of fame and eſtimation were not as well ſpotted therewith as are the brothell houſes, whoſe graceleſſe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitaunts are limmes of the deuill. And lamentable is it to ſee in Englande at this daye, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Courtyer to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſtincking ſinne is ſo common, that it is rather accompted an ordinarie paſtime than an odible offence,
<note place="margin">whordom accounted no Sinne</note> which as it ſtincketh before the face of God, ſo is it left vnpuniſhed, ſauing now and then in Bridewell, (a place ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for the redreſſe of ſuche vice, as I know not how it might haue bene put to a better vſe to haue benefited the common wealth) or ſometime likewiſe in London with a little carting it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, though to many that diſcrue it come not to the promotion. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:12421:5"/>according to the olde prouerb, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſometime a frende in court than a penny in purſe. But take heede I ſay yee Magiſtrates, beware of parcialitie. Yet to ſaye truth, whether carting or a flappe wyth a Fore tayle, all is to one purpoſe, and therefore euen as good ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a whit as neuer the better, for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doth but make them careleſſe and ſhameleſſe and rather to continue in theire beaſtlineſſe than bring them to honeſty and repentaunce of their euill. Wherefore if it be not the ſoner other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe looked to and a ſharper ſauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for ſuch filthye whores &amp; whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, yee ſhall ſhortlye in place of honeſt modeſt Matrones and vndefiled virgins haue the Realme repleniſhed with a company of cankered, corrupte, &amp; lothſome whores, whereof the filthy flocke encreaſeth a pace and to faſt. And here may yee ſee and bcholde howe vice aboundeth for lacke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſte rewarde that therunto belongeth, which ſhould be ſeuere iuſtice, for neglecting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as the Magiſtrates incurre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:12421:6"/>of God, ſo are the wicked that ſtill ſleepe in theire ſinne incouraged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and continue the members of the deuill. But oh ye Magiſtrates looke to your charge, &amp; oh yee lothſome whores and whoremongers let Sodome and Gommorra be your looking glaſſes, wherin without your repentaunce and amendement of your beaſtlye lyfe, yee may moſte plainely beholde your vtter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But now to proceede,
<note place="margin">The abuſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day.</note> as concerning the Sabboth daye or rather the Lordes day, how well it is obſerued: I reporte mee to thoſe delicate feeders, whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts euen iuſt vpon that daye, when they ſhoulde be at Churche to heare the deuine ſeruice and haue theire duties taught them, muſt then forſoth runne a gadding from market to market to make prouiſion for a diſhe of needenot for the latter courſe, when there is alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye to much for the firſt, which waſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful money were better beſtowed in the workes of Faith, helping by charity thy needefull brethren that haue not ſo wel
<pb facs="tcp:12421:6"/>to fyl their hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grie bellies, (but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſcant thought on.) Alſo other ſome there bee, who when they ſhould congregate themſelues in the Temple or Church, which is a place appointed to inuocate the name of GOD and to praiſe him for his manifolde benefites, then are they packed vp togither in Tauernes and Alehouſes, yelling for vittailes to fill their filthy paunche.</p>
            <p>But oh beaſtlye bellie, whether is the Lorde thy God or thou fyrſte to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Iwys I remember there was not long a go a godlye order made in London by the Lorde Maior and the worſhipfull the Aldermen, that the doores of tauernes and vittailing hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould be kept ſhut in ſeruice time, which order is comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable, if it were obſerued according to the good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that the doores ſhould I ſaye, be kept ſhut in ſeruice time, to keepe out ſuch bellie bibbers, but now they firſt fill and furniſhe their houſes w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geſtes and then they ſhutte the doores.</p>
            <p>But (alas) what mockery is this with
<pb facs="tcp:12421:7"/>God &amp; the Magiſtrates?
<note place="margin">God and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked by the typplers which are but harbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thriftes.</note> for the which, vnleſſe they maye feele the ſmarte, it wil be the longer the worſe, before it be better. For in vaine are good lawes made vnleſſe they be thorowlye execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and therefore I wiſhe that there were certaine in eche parriſhe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that on the Saboth daye might vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite the vitailing houſes, and as well to make report of thoſe that are the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of ſuch geſtes (that they might for ſo receiuing of them bee conſidered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſeruing,) as alſo to driue from thence thoſe gredie glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that minde ſo much theire bellies, and bring them to Gods banketting houſe that he might haue more ſtore of geſts to feede Faithfullye with hungrye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites vpon his holy worde which is the comfortable foode that nouriſheth the ſoule of man, and that the Children and ſeruaunts by the godly and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lyfe of thoſe theire Parentes and Maiſters, might both learne to knowe their duties to God, praiſing his holye name, as alſo theire due obedience to
<pb facs="tcp:12421:7"/>their elders,
<note place="margin">The want of good en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſample of Elders is the diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of Youth.</note> for want of whoſe good examples and their to much libertie gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the riotous youth (the more is the pitie) runne to faſt hedlong to deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But no maruell, for neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an euill tree bring forthe good fruite, nor thornes can bring forth Grapes, and therefore ſuch carpenters ſuch tooles, and ſuch maiſters ſuch ſeruants.</p>
            <p>But yet a little more concerning the abuſing of the Lordes day, vpon the which almoſt euen as though of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, the beares at Parris garden muſte be bayted,
<note place="margin">Beatbay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sabboth abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble.</note> but ſo vglye are not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beares as the ydle lookers on are beaſtly. God for hys mercye defende that the deuyll baite not the ſoules of ſuche as delight ſo beaſtlie to ſpende the day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde God of Saboth.</p>
            <p>But to proceede, on that daye the maiſters and ſchollers of Fence muſte ſhewe themſelues and their cunning, whereas after oft meeting with foynes and floriſhes and dealing of deſperate and boſterous blowes, they part wyth broken heads, maimed armes &amp; hands,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:8"/>and bloody faces, finiſhing vp the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with ſuch ſwearing &amp; terrible tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of GOD, that it is great wonder that God w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſworde of hys diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure layeth not on loade amongſt them beating their weapons to their heades and them into the earth. Loe, thus is the day of the Lorde turned to the daye of bloudſheading and blaſphemie tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſchole houſes of Fence, naye rather of miſchiefe,
<note place="margin">Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes of Fence, brede thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to fede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gallowes</note> for thereby are to many loitering ſchollers &amp; vacabundes encouraged to miſchief, bearing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo bolde of their Fence that they are as readye to keepe a ſtanding in the hye wayes as the ſtrongeſt theefe in England, and ſo in the ende to many (the more is the pitie,) for all theire cunning, are to ſeeke of Fence to keepe their necks from the halter. Loe, what folly Fence bredeth. And thus wyth theſe &amp; many other abuſes is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes daye polluted. But let vs not thinke that the Lorde our God who puniſhed wyth Death the man for gathering ſtickes onely on the Saboth daye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numeri.</hi> 15</note> wyll
<pb facs="tcp:12421:8"/>leaue vs vnpuniſhed that ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſe the ſame which ſo expreſſely he hath commaunded to be kept holy and appointed to worſhip hym on. Let vs be aſſured wee ſhall knowe the price thereof as well, as alſo for the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull wickedneſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherwyſe raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth amongſt vs that are voide of all Godlineſſe and full of abhomination and ſinne: For truely there is amongſt vs no pureneſſe in heart, no truthe in mouthe, no vprightneſſe in dealing, but doubleneſſe, fraude, deceite and guile. Brotherly loue is cleane bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. For who can almoſt ſpeake well of an other? and charitie is become ſo colde that the fruites of Faith faynt thorowe cankered couetouſneſſe, who is ſo deepely crept into the corrupt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men ſo generally,
<note place="margin">The Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes hath eaten awaye the good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of England.</note> that who almoſt is not therewyth infected? and to whome as the terme goeth, all is not fiſhe that commeth to nette, and ſo they haue that they woulde haue, they care not howe they come by it? which as it is to manifeſt and appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:9"/>ſo lykewiſe to lamentable to beholde that amongſt thoſe that take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the name of Chriſtians ſuche crooked conditions ſhoulde be vſed as hereafter ſhall be declared.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning couetouſneſſe, which whether it be to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant with vs, let thoſe of reaſon iudge, who ſeing and well noting the great and gratious bleſſing of God vpon the earthe, which hath ſo plentifullye brought forth and yelded her increaſe of all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye for the foode of man (thankes to God therefore,) yet notwithſtanding, a dearth to remaine, and vpon no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſaue onely thorow the curſed coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe of rauening Cormorauntes, that (ſo they may fyll their bottomleſſe bagges) care not what nor whom they deuour. I would to god the Graziours, who thorowe theire greedye ioyning of paſture to paſture for to muche lukers ſake,
<note place="margin">Graziours and great ſheepe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moraunts in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale.</note> filling faſter their coffers tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they fatte their cattell: and alſo the vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſheepemaiſters, that to encreaſe and augment ſuch needeleſſe and not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie
<pb facs="tcp:12421:9"/>number of ſheepe as nowe there are, hauing ſpoiled thereby whole vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages and townes, (to the great decaye of tillage,) were not I ſaye the chiefeſt occaſions of thys preſent miſchieuous miſery: thorow the deuiliſh dealing of which two kindes of people, we haue been and to lately were forced to ſeeke in forreine countreys our breadcorne, whereas before ſuch gredye couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe raigned, we had plenty &amp; ynough at home to ſerue our ſelues and to ſpare for others our neighbors, till now that the ſheepe which God had ordeined for man, are by couetous men encreaſed to ſuche noiſome numbers, that they haue deuoured men and driuen them from their dwellings,
<note place="margin">Many ſheepe and fewe plou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land ſwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me wyth beggars.</note> who wyth their wyues and children begge aboute the countreis, their houſes being ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen: but better were therefore more ploughes and fewer ſheepe, than ſo many ſheepe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> encreaſe of beggers. But, oh meruellous brutiſheneſſe of thoſe people that for the exceſſiue gaine of paſture money, preferre the bruite
<pb facs="tcp:12421:10"/>beaſtes before their poore brethren, and that to feede beaſtes ſterue Chriſtians. ★ But why doe yet ſo oppreſſe my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and marre the faces of the pore ſaith the Lorde by the mouth of his ſeruaunt and Prophet Eſaye,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 3.</note> that ſo ioyne one houſe to another and bring one land ſo to another y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the poore can get no grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but that they may dwel vpon the earth alone? and for ſuch doth Hell open hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mouth and gape for ſayth the Prophet, whoe threatneth the wrath of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch. And Abacuc likewiſe in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abacuc.</hi> 2.</note> I referre thee to the place the reading whereof God graunt may be a warning. But are the farmers in this point altogither clean and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe? nay would to God ther were not to manye in Englande whoſe barnes God hath well repleniſhed wyth ſtore,
<note place="margin">The coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tous Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the good gifts of God.</note> that both ſay and doe, as not long ſince I hearde a rich and wealthy farmer ſay &amp; bound it with an othe, that he would ſell hys Corne at ſuch a pryce, or kepe it tyl the myce eate it. But (as I fear me) there be to many farmers of that chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye.
<pb facs="tcp:12421:10"/>So no maruell though ſo greate a ſcarcitye of breadecorne as of late, hath bene, whiche woulde haue bene fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of courſe but for the gratious prouiſion of the woorthy Marchanntes and Cityzens of London that fed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as well the Cytye as a greate parte of the Countrey aboute them.
<note place="margin">The wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of London.</note> The Lorde proſper, bleſſe and holde hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hand ouer that Cyty and inhabitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that are ſo carefull for their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. But againe to my matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth I was in hand. As thoſe wordes and deedes of ſuche Farmers are not Chriſtianlyke, ſo are they not the beſt members in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as they vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſing the good gifts of GOD, enhauncing the price of Corne of meere couetouſneſſe to enryche theym ſelues to the greate detrimente and harme of theire neyghboures and brethren, whoſe wealth thereby howe muche it is of late increaſed, the ſumpteouſneſſe and brauery of their children doth well declare, who in many places in engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:12421:11"/>are at theſe dayes growen to ſuche a fineneſſe that they are more redier for houſes of the court,
<note place="margin">The follie of parents maketh vnthrifty children.</note> than the plough, &amp; ſo giuen to ydleneſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they holde great ſcorne to treade the furrowes and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their fathers ſteppes, But nowe the father to Cart, the ſonne to Court. Well, well, prouender pricketh, and welth I ſaye maketh wantons, which God graunt of the getters to be truely come by and with vpright conſcience, for according to the olde prouerbe, wel gotten well ſpent, God ſende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plough more frendes and followers. But yet a little further concerning couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. How lamentable is it to ſee and beholde the number of men that dailye ſayle in the payement of their dettes, and as they tearme it play bankroute? I meane not thoſe (neither deſerue they the name) whoſe ſubſtaunce by caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of fyre, by ſpoyling of Pirottes, or thorowe force of ſtormie and tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous weather, by ſhypwracke wyth the ſourges of the deepe ſeas are peryſhed, vnto which and many other perills the
<pb facs="tcp:12421:11"/>marchauntes aduenturers thorow the ſufferance of god are ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times ſubiect and by ſuch meanes ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their wealth plucked from them and they empoueriſhed, who as they gladly and willingly would, but haue not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſatiſfye their creditours, ſo are they yet in thys reſpect to be holpen, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and borne withall, (and God forbidde that otherwyſe it ſhoulde bee.) But of thoſe ſhameleſſe ones I meane, of which nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of late there hath bene to many, that when thorowe their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite they haue heaped togither a maſſe of treaſure in money and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, they ſodainely abſent and hyde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and playe bankroute, an vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianlike playe and to a deuiliſhe and wicked ende and purpoſe, for hauing wherewith to ſatiſfye and content all their creditours, they will eyther paye nothing at all or as little as they liſte, and thus they reape the corne that is not their owne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> and ſpoile ſometyme thereby the ſucking fatherleſſe childe. And by thys wicked meanes is many
<pb facs="tcp:12421:12"/>an honeſt man brought to an after deal and oftentymes vndoone, wyth whoſe goodes thoſe theeues enryche themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues:
<note place="margin">A wylfull bancktout &amp; a theefe all one.</note> Theeues I ſay, for thefte it is and no better, and yet is it nowe a dayes made an ordinarye occupation. And where is the redreſſe, or which of them (as beefore I ſayd,) doth not what hym liſteth? Well, woful is it to ſee that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians ſuch partes ſhould be played, and more lamentable is it that ſtill it is ſuffred. Couetouſneſſe is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous poyſon, and yet though loth I am to wryte it, I know no eſtate or vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in England that is not infected therewyth euen from the mountaines to the valleyes. And therfore to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude wher the rage of corrupt couetouſneſſe raygneth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right of iuſtice muſt nedes be miniſhed, I would it wer not ſo, but (alas) it is to manifeſt.‡ But muſt not God needes punniſh vs in whom there is no truthe nor knoweledge of hym,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſeas.</hi> 4.</note> but vntruthe, lying, ſwearing, adultry thefte, and all manner of ſuche fylthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Are theſe things a declaration of
<pb facs="tcp:12421:12"/>brotherly loue amongſt vs?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gallat.</hi> 5.</note> doe we as we woulde be done vnto? loue we our neighbours as our ſelues, that thus byte and deuour one an other? Oh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable wickedneſſe and oh miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and peſtilent people. But hath our Heauenly Father reuealed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of his Goſpell vnto vs that wee in ſuch ſhamefull wyſe ſhould abuſe hys great mercy? no, no, wherfore to the Carnall Goſpellers as well as to the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Papiſtes, I ſaye: bee no longer careleſſe, but learne to knowe the will of the Lorde, and doe it. Let worde and deede be one. Profeſſe and followe or elſe we are but ſlaunderers &amp; enimies of the Goſpell, and the bleſſing and great good gyftes of God (the lyght of hys Goſpell) is euill beſtowed vpon vs, ſhewing our ſelues to be the enimies of Ieſu Chriſt and of his truth the ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. Counterfaytes are wee and plaine diſſemblers wyth God and the Worlde, yea, euen a people in whome ſcant one ſparke or propertye appereth that vnto Chriſtians appertayneth:
<pb facs="tcp:12421:13"/>for if we were Chriſtians we woulde followe Chriſtes lore, ‡ who being the Way,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.</note> the Truth and life, we renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and go from the Waye, decline from Truth, and forſaking Life doe thorow our wicked meanes ſeeke to our ſelues Death and diſtruction. The Lorde bee mercifull vnto vs, for we are growen to this point, that we neyther feare the Lorde our God nor ſtande in awe of the Magiſtrates. And what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, but for that the good lawes made by them for the puniſhement of offenders are no better executed but in a manner eche one left to himſelfe to doe what he liſteth? But truely euen as much doe the Magiſtrates offende GOD in not puniſhing the offenders, as they that commit the offence. For all this euill commeth of ſufferaunce,
<note place="margin">Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce breedeth inconueni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence.</note> but to muche ſufferaunce cauſeth care and to muche ſufferaunce breedeth diſobedience. And is it not ſufferaunce that tickeleth the talketiue tonges of the wicked and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll dyſpoſed, ſo ſhamefullye and ſclaunderouſlye to reporte and ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:12421:13"/>euill of the bleſſed worde of GOD and doctrine of Ieſu Chriſt, and of the Preachers and Teachers of the ſame, vnreuerentlye ieſting and ſcoffing at them, as dailye they doe, euen like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Diotrephes that of arrogancye exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> diſpiſed the doctrine of the Apoſtles, ieſting at them with maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wordes? And what is it elſe but ſufferaunce that ſo animateth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Archpapiſtes ſo ſtoutely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their Romiſh heretical errour, contrarye to the will of God and their due obedience to their Prince? But no maruell therefore, though the common ſort ſo careleſly continue in their euill,
<note place="margin">The Arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>papiſtes Ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to miſchiefe.</note> when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ringleaders to miſchiefe, (the Archpapiſtes,) beyng the maintayners of Idolatrye, breakers of Wedlocke, theeues, murderers, and rebels againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince in Gods and hir procedings, are thus ſuffered to wallowe ſtill in the poyſoned puddell of their wicked wyll, and yet remaine vnpunniſhed. But yet as it is not ynough but a perillous matter for one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to cal another thefe,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:14"/>vnleſſe he be able to proue it, So I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to trye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to be true which here I haue written of them, wyll therefore make due proofe thereof, as well for mine owne diſcharge as alſo to ſatiſfye the reader.</p>
            <p>And firſt that they are maintainers of Idolatrye,
<note place="margin">Archpapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayners of Idolatry.</note> the great number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whome God hath yet ſpared alyue, wytneſſe wyth mee, howe they when they were in authority, or rather when God ſuffered them to bee as whippes &amp; ſcourges to vs for our forgetfulneſſe of God: how they then I ſaye, thorowe their violent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſion, forced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people (to the great derogation and diſhonour of God,) to erect Idolls and garniſh the Church and Houſe of God with Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, which (as in the booke of Wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſpecified) neyther haue bene fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning nor ſhall continue to the ende,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 14.</note> but haue only bene inuented thorow the wealthy Idleneſſe of men: but wherewith yet they I ſaye then ſo charmed and enchaunted the mindes of many of the ſimple ignoraunt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:14"/>wyth theyr Idolatrous infection, as that I woulde to GOD there were not nowe in theſe dayes to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye that worſhipping in hugger mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in Coffers and Corners their ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Babilonicall blockbabes, thynke they pleaſe God better than to come to bee inſtructed by the hearing of the worde of GOD preached. Thus haue they I ſaye ſeduced the people from the true and liuing Lorde to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe ſtraunge and vnknowen Gods and honouring of abhominable Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ‡ whiche is the begynning and ende of all euill,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſhewing themſelues thereby to bee the manifeſt enimies of the Almighty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deutro.</hi> 13.</note> and as Moiſes doth note and name them, falſe Prophetes, drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and maintainers of wicked Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrye, which beyng a ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and an abhomination ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and haynons in the ſight of God, as that hee hath alwayes abhorred and extremely punniſhed it: yet are they wyth tooth and naile ſupporters of the ſame. Wherfore as God by the mouth
<pb facs="tcp:12421:15"/>of Moyſes playnely expreſſeth that they ought not to be pitied nor reſerued and kept as they yet are,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.16.</note> ſo doth he alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt them their reward,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieremy.</hi> 26.</note> which is that they ſhould be deſtroyed wythout com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zachar.</hi> 13.</note> And accordingly did Elia with 450. falſe Prophetes of Baal at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> broke Kiſon.
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Kings.</hi> 16 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.</note> Alſo Ioſia who burned the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Prieſtes vppon the altares of the Idols. But nowe to goe forwarde wyth my proofe: Breakers of wedlocke I ſayd they were, as moſt true it is they be. For although that Chriſt as by the autority of the ſcriptures, doth permit vnto euery man without exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cannot liue chaſte,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.</note> as well ſpirituall as temporall, his wife, to liue togither in that holy and bleſſed ſtate of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ordayned by God for the auoyding of hatefull whordome ★ who being once coupled according to the lawes of God no man ought to ſeperate or put aſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der yet notwithſtanding that,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuitic.</hi> 17.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 19. <hi>Marke.</hi> 10.</note> how did they (I ſay) abuſe and ſhamefullye ſeperate diuers and ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry of the miniſterie then matched in matrimony,
<note place="margin">Papiſtes breakers of wedlock</note> dealing as cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>elly
<pb facs="tcp:12421:15"/>wyth them therefore as if they had committed ſome notorious offence, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowing in the miniſtery then, that to be neceſſary, which Chriſte in his time for his Apoſtels did ſee to be conuenient and neceſſary? And Paul witneſſing the ſame, ſayth:
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 7.</note> It is better to marrye than to burne, but he ſayth not, It is better to take a whore than to marrye, as a greate many of their beaſtly broode of lecherous Maſſeprieſtes did, who as they woulde not marry, ſo liued they not <hi>Casté,</hi> but <hi>Cauté</hi> played the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, and ſome <hi>Palam</hi> defiled theyr neighboures wiues, committed dayly inceſt and were euen fellowe compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Sodomites, whoſe beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe theſe Mitered men oft wincked at and woulde not ſee the wyckedneſſe of their God Bels belly gods, but looked thorow the fyngers at them, as ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wel know to their ſhame though they ſay nay and lye as their generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath always bene accuſtomed, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will do other. But though for their wicked whoredome they haue in thys
<pb facs="tcp:12421:16"/>world eſcaped the puniſhment due for the ſame,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebru.</hi> 13.</note> yet ſhall God ſhut them out of hys Kingdome into euerlaſting fier, vnleſſe they repent, which God graunt they may. But now to proceede, thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues alſo I ſayde they were,
<note place="margin">Papiſtes are theues <hi>Iohn.</hi> 10.</note> ‡ and ſo S. Iohn calleth them that come not but to ſteale &amp; deſtroy, of which number they are &amp; ſo ſhewed themſelues to be when they not only did breake into Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, ſtealing from vs the fruit of life, but alſo lopped and deſtroyed the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches that plenteouſlye yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded forth the fruite therof,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieremy.</hi> 12.</note> ‡ Treading downe the Vineyard and pleaſant por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lorde, of malitious purpoſe to leaue it waſte and to make it a wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, ſtealing away the heauenly treaſure of Gods Sanctuary, and wyth conſciences moſte filthily defiled filling and repleniſhing the Lords houſe with robbery &amp; falſhed, and therfore agayne I ſay theeues and alſo enimies to God, that loue him not: ‡ For how can they
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4.</note> loue God whome they haue not ſeene, when thei loued not their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with
<pb facs="tcp:12421:16"/>whome they were dayly conuerſaunt? For it is not ſo long agoe to bee yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, how vnmercifully they dealte wyth the ſeely faythfull flocke of Ieſu Chriſt, who by the diuine inſpiration and good gyft of the holy Ghoſt, ſetting forth the glory of God &amp; plentifully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the holſome and dilectable doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Ieſu Chriſt, wherwith almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty god had richly repleniſhed them, and wherwyth they dayly taught and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs to know the wil of our heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father. They did I ſay forbid to teach the truthe, and would not ſuffer them to preach Chriſte vnto the people, but, notwithſtanding the expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God almighty who ſtraytly charged them ‡ that they ſhoulde not touche his annoynted,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 105.</note> nor do his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets any harme, yet did they rigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recompence them, turmoyling and toſſing them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt to piller, mocked them, buffeted them, with roddes beat them, impriſoned them, hungerſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> ‡ and euen as Cain to hys brother Abell, ſo did theſe Tiraunts
<pb facs="tcp:12421:17"/>moſt cruelly murder their innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<note place="margin">Papiſts at murderers</note> and with fier conſumed to aſhes the fleſh of Ieſus Chriſt in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, ‡ whoſe beautifull feete brought vs ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of good things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 10.</note> euen the peace of the Goſpell of Chriſt our Sauiour. And why did they thus to them? ‡ bycauſe their workes were good and their owne euill,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> they being of the offpring of thoſe that killed the Lord Ieſus and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes and nowe likewiſe thirſted for the bloud of theſe innocent martirs, and therefore murderers from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 15.</note> ‡ But now I cal to remembrance how Samuell the zealous Prophete of the Lord calling for King Agag the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy of God and murderer of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to whome after he had ſayde theſe words (as thy ſword hath made wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> childeleſſe, ſo ſhal thy mother be childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,) did then in the zeale of God he we King Agag in peeces, Oh cruel murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and ſheader of innocent bloud,
<note place="margin">The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of a murderer.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily rewarded. But if Agag being a King was not ſpared, how well haue theſe then deſerued to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſye,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:17"/>being continuall committers of ſhameful things, mercileſſe oppreſſors, cruell perſecutours of Fatherleſſe and Wyddowes, ſhedders of innocente bloud, vnſatiable murderers wylfully working the mercyleſſe motions of theire hatefull heartes, thorowe whoſe terrible tyrannye many mothers were lefte child cleſſe, and many children fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe and motherleſſe, that were of the familye of the faythfull in Ieſu Chriſt? of which moſt terrible tragedye though the whole worlde can witneſſe yet remaine thoſe murderers vnrecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with Agags iuſt rewarde. But laſt of all that I ſayde they were rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious,
<note place="margin">Papiſts a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rebellious.</note> let their ſtubborne and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent behauiour towardes their Prince be witneſſe, in that they ſo arrogantlye contend with their Soueraigne, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and reſiſting the worde of GOD, which by the Princes moſte Gracious proceedings, to the vnſpeakeable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of all hir graces true faythfull and louing Subiectes, is (thanked be God therefore) moſte entierly and truely ſet
<pb facs="tcp:12421:18"/>forth and taught, which they vtterlye deteſt, and followe the imaginations of their owne heartes and ſtill continue in their euil. Loe, theſe be of them that had ſo blinded the worlde wyth their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait holineſſe, that they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and thought to be without ſpot, and yet moſte grieuous tranſgreſſours and full of all iniquitye and poyſon, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to doe that whych by Goddes law they are commaunded, and regarding rather the vſurping monſtrous Pope that Romiſh beaſt and Antichriſt, than fearing God and reſpecting theire due obedience to their Soueraigne &amp; moſte gratious Prince and liege Ladye, who as Salomon ſayth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouer.</hi> 16.</note> ought to be feared as a Lion, and whoſe diſpleaſure is a meſſanger of death: who therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they feare not I ſaye for the loue that ſaythfull Subiectes beare to their Prince of duety,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.</note> yet I thynke they ſhoulde feare, loue and humbly obeye hir for the loue and feare of him ★ that ſhall call the heauens from aboue and the earth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman.</hi> 13.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50.</note> that he may iudge hys peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:18"/>★ againſt which day of vengeaunce when ſhall bee opened the ryghteous iudgement of GOD,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13.</note> ſuch ſtubburn-hearted contencious rebelles that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe iniquitye, diſobeye and reſiſte the truthe and the higher powers which is the ordinaunce of GOD, and that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers cannot or wyll not repent, doe but heape vnto themſelues the wrath of God who will reward them with trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and anguiſh of ſoule to euerlaſting damnation.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 46.</note>
               <note place="margin">A charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes.</note> Wherfore O ye preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous prieſts that are of an hye ſtomack but farre from righteouſneſſe, as yee haue bene terrible tyrauntes and your handes full of bloud, ſo now put from you the violence and myſchiefe of your mindes: and as ye haue not ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye but arrogantly fought againſte the God of glory, ſo call now to him for the aſſiſtaunce of his holy ſpirit that it may pleaſe him therewith to ſtrengthen you agaynſt your aduerſary the diuell, that hee no longer bewitche you nor wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your mindes from God: for now ye ſayle &amp; ſtumble in your iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:12421:19"/>being ignoraunt as yong children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> and bycauſe yee wyll not hearken vnto the voyce of God pronounced by his choſen veſſels, hee ſuffereth you to be tangled, ſnared, and to fall backwardes in youre wylfulneſſe.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 1.</note> Leane therefore no longer vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weake ſtaffe of antiquity which both you and many men ground them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon, doing as their fathers did, for as well our Forefathers as alſo our ſelues haue done vnrighteouſlye and haue not kept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way which the higheſt commaunded vs, and therfore cuſtome without truth is not alloweable, but is an olde errour. Pray thefore vnto the Lorde God to open your eyes that yee may ſpye out the wonderous things in the lawe of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 119</note> ★ Seke him with your whole heartes vnfaynedly that ye may walk in his wayes, leauing the wicked and wylfull blindneſſe wherein you haue ſo long bene nouſeled, and be no longer as Fooles that make good ſport of Synne, but foreſee your wickedneſſe which as the Lorde according as the Scriptures make mention, hath pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb facs="tcp:12421:19"/>in Princes being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt, and to whome he hath giuen the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his people, ſo will he not ſurely leaue it vnreco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penced in popiſh prieſts, but aſwel in prieſtes as in al people ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of what vocation or calling ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that repining the truthe of Ieſus Chriſt and wilfully wallowing in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and ſinne careleſlye continue in the ſame, he wyll hiſite and for their rewarde giue them to drinke of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and heauy wrath. Wherefore I aſmuch as in mee is, exhort you in the Lorde to become obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t children ‡ and to retourne wyth the prodigall childe from your groſſe feeding on ſwinecods and with hearty repentaunce meekely and humbly to tourne to your heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Father,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 25.</note> feeding on hys heauenly worde, that wee your brethren might reioice of the finding of you that were loſte &amp; reuiuing of you that were dead.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 5.</note> ‡ Submit therfore your ſelues in lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of heart vnder the mighty hand of God and ſhewe your due obedience and bee ſubiecte to your moſt gracious
<pb facs="tcp:12421:20"/>and mercifull Prince, be no more diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe wilfull but godly willing, arme your ſelues I ſaye wyth ſingleneſſe of heart as miniſters to worke the will of our heauenlye Father, not compelled but willinglye, not wyth proude and lordely ſtomacks but meekely, giuing good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to the flock of Ieſu Chriſt, of which as yee haue bene mercileſſe ſpoſlers, deſtroyers and famiſhers, ſo now thorowe the moſt gracious opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almightye yee may become repairers, feeders and nouriſhers of the ſame, that when the chiefe ſhepehearde ſhall appeare ‡ hee may exalt you when the time is come,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 5.</note> that then ye maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an incorruptible crowne of glory, which I beſech God for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſake to graunt vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ys may I ſaye become hys ſeruauntes and wyth ioy in him poſſeſſe the earth during his good pleaſure, and after thys lyfe to haue the fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lyfe euerlaſting. Be therfore no longer the mayſters of errour puſſed vp wyth pride, but the Diſciples of truth, &amp; ſhewe your ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:12421:20"/>no longer as brute beaſtes naturallye made to be deſtroyed, whoſe heartes God hath ſo hardened for that yee ſhuld not hearken vnto his worde, bicauſe he would haue you rooted from the earth. But leaue in tyme your diſobedience, for diſobedient children ſhall finde no reſt, wherefore if yee ſtill preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye proceede as yee haue begonne ‡ knowe that preſumptuouſneſſe goeth before diſtruction and after a proude ſtomacke there followeth a fall,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouer.</hi> 16. <hi>Deutro.</hi> 17. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5.</note> for the Lorde abhorreth all ſuche as are of a proude ſtomacke and wyll not ſuffer them to eſcape vnpunniſhed ★ but will recompence them theire wyckedneſſe and deſtroye them in theire owne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice ‡ hycauſe they rebell againſt hym.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 94</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 107.</note> Therefore I ſaye once againe as one that from the bottome of my hearte wyſhe your conuerſion to GOD, take heede and tempt the Lorde God no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neyther preſume to muche of the mercye of your Prince, for yf ye doe, ſurely God wyll in the ende put in hir Graces heart, as moſt excellent ‡ euen
<pb facs="tcp:12421:21"/>ſent of and by him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> 6</note> for the punniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the wicked and to the praiſe of the good (to conſider) that as a Mother, who being tender ouer hir Children with ouermuch cockering them, doth but make them ſo wanton and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that they regarde hir not, and ſo ſparing the rodde hurteth hir Children and harmeth hir ſelfe, ſo likewyſe that hir grace thorowe hir greate lenity and mercy in to long ſuffering you doth but make you the more forgetfull of youre dueties to your ſo gracious a Prince, &amp; moue you the rather to worke your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues woe, wyth practiſing of that that might be hurtful to hir highnes, which the almighty god of Iſrael defend. But yet is it to be feared and iuſt cauſe hath hir Maieſtye to bee out of hope of youre conuerſion to God and to haue you hir faythfull and true Subiects hereafter, that in ſo long a tyme of reſpecte haue not hadde the grace to learne to feare God and to knowe your duties to hym and youre ſo gratious and mercyfull a Prince.‡ Iob ſayth that if a tree bee cut
<pb facs="tcp:12421:21"/>downe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.</note> there is ſome hope ſayth hee that it will ſproute out and ſhoote forth the braunches againe, and a roote being waxen olde and deade in the grounde, yet when the ſtock getteth the cente of the water it will budde a newe &amp; bring forth bowes: but howe long hath the Queenes Maieſtye euen as a mother of mercye, thorow hir gracious goodneſſe and great lenitye made the tryall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in you, reſeruing and watering you all this while with hir mercye, to trye thereby if ſhee could cauſe you to bring forth the floriſhing brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull buddes of repentaunte heartes, thereby as well to benefite your ſelues as alſo others thorow the good example of your humbleneſſe, who notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtubbornely continue the longer the worſe, ſhewing your ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be of thoſe trees or roote that Iob ſpeaketh of, but rather playnelye painting forthe yourſelues in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte colours and ſhewing your ſelues to be the ſame that certaynely yee are,
<note place="margin">A graceles papiſt and a rotten roote one in effect.</note> euen rotten rootes voide of Godly ſappe
<pb facs="tcp:12421:22"/>and into whome no inoyſture of godly vnderſtanding or knowledge can enter. Wherefore according to the ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſte by the mouthe of Mathewe, Ye muſt be plucked vp, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen downe and caſte into the fyer and wholly reiected as wylfull Hereticks ‡ agaynſte whome no admonition wyll preuayle.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> But now my thinke I heare ſome parciall Papiſte ſaye: beholde I praye you the charity of this Goſpeller, this Proteſtante is in hys extremities, what? my thincke he woulde haue the poore men worſe handled than they are alreadye, being meetely well trounced and hampered I trowe, as the Tower, Fleete, Marſhalſee and ſuch other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can witneſſe. In deede ſir ye ſaye true, they haue bene ſo yll beſtead, ſo ſore hurte and ſo extremely dealt with, as that thoſe that bee in worſe lyking haue no cauſe to complayne. So ſome of them are ſo foule fallen awaye that they are growen from a horſeloade to a cartloade, which betokeneth no want of victuals and good cheriſhing, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:12421:22"/>of to much pampering. Well I ſay the Diuell is not without friends as now right wel appeareth, by whoſe meanes theſe terrible tirants that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rebell wyth peril as traytours to God and their Prince, than obey with reſt as obedient ſubiectes, who rather may be ſayd to haue bene to long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in places of pleaſure, than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted as priſoners, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering how well they were vſed and prouided for, who hauing then but to much liberty are now fette further at large to haue more Elbowe rome and ſcope, to take their pleaſure on progreſſe aboute the countreye to refreſhe them ſelues as though before they had bene miſuſed or had receiued to much iniury, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if they had their iuſt deſert, Death, Death ſhould and oughte to bee their reward. But loe, the filthy foules are flowen, the bloudy birds are vncaged whoe flickering abroade are making wings for a new pray, which God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apoynt them of. But as it is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and needefull that the Prince
<pb facs="tcp:12421:23"/>(whome God long preſerue) haue good regard by hir taſter apointed, to auoide the purpoſed miſchiefe from hir bodye by poyſoning of meates, (which wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and crayterous Subiectes bothe haue and maye attempte that ſeeke to aduaunce and eſtablyſhe themſelues and the wickedneſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they embrace,) ſo is it moſt neceſſarye and conuenient that a regarde bee had by the Prince to hir people committed to hir charge, leaſt the venemous priuye perſuaſion and deuiliſhe counſell of this Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian rable dooe ſlaye and poyſon the ſoules of the ſimple Subiectes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by might enſue as well perill to the Prince as diſtruction of the common wealth, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty God defend for hys mercye ſake, and graunt that thorowe thys to long ſufferaunce the lyke furious flame flaſhe not againe ſodenly abrode as once it did before any ſparke was feared to haue bene kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for according to the olde prouerbe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is bredde in the bone wyll ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer out of the fleſhe, &amp; ſo will the vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb facs="tcp:12421:23"/>broode neuer leaue enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering of poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſtes is to work miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> whoſe ſtudy as it hath euermore bene to deuiſe &amp; imagine how to worke miſchiefe, ſo cannot I ſaye the bytter braunches of that trayterous and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous tree yelde better fruite, and therfore are to be conſidered according, for ſecret and perillous hath their priuy poyſoned practiſe and packing euer ben from the beginning,
<note place="margin">A Papiſte enuimy to God and traitout to his prince.</note> as experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath taught, to the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (the more was the pitye) both of Prince and people, whereof let auncient ſtories and Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles be witneſſe. And I woulde that now the ſame bloudye and murdering broode were not in hande to brewe that miſchiefe which God graunt them ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to tonne but that they may bee ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their owne lycker. Well, well, they that wyll may ſee the wyckedneſſe of that generation, but therefore are ſuch ſcabbed ſheepe no longer to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered which doe but infecte the ſounde flocke. And (alas) that ſufferaunce tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to much lenitys ſhoulde onely cauſe ſuch careleſſe wicked men ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye
<pb facs="tcp:12421:24"/>to worke their owne diſtruction, wheras the law (if it were iuſtly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)‡ being ordayned for the vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, diſobedient, murderes of Fathers and Mothers, manſlayers, whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. &amp;c, might bring them to God and be a terrour to other euil diſpoſed, who now thorow their being borne wythall are rather encouraged and boldened in their euill. Wherfore as the corne doth better grow vppe where no cockle is to cumber it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouer.</hi> 25.</note> ‡ ſo take the droſſe from the ſiluer and there ſhall be a cleane veſſell thereof, and as the common wealth is the better mayntayned and flouriſheth wher the law is worthily executed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the offenders, ſo woulde the Goſpel of our ſauiour Chriſt bee more willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier embraced in the heartes of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ignorant ones, if the Archerimies were cut of from the face of the earth, whoſe ſtubborne and preſumpteous reſiſtaunce of Gods and the Queenes procedings, is now the onely let, which as it highlye offendeth the Maieſtye of God, ſo is it an occaſion of the increaſe
<pb facs="tcp:12421:24"/>of euill to the further prouocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wrath. Therefore as it is good by all meanes poſſyble to cure an infected member,
<note place="margin">Neceſſarie and preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t remedy in extremity.</note> ſo is it much better if it be found vncurable to cut it of, than that it ſhoulde infect the whole &amp; ſounde body. And wheras cankered corſies in curriſh patiences are ſo feſtered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the pretious medicine of mercy may not cure them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt of neceſſity, iuſtice, a medicine more ſharpe &amp; apt for ſuch a <hi>Nunq ſanus,</hi> be miniſtred.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 3.</note> Wherfore let the crooked ones be made ſtraight &amp; the rough ones made plaine. And hye time it is, for they do now but lie like dombe dogges or as rauening and deuouring woolues lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for their pray, their bellies not yet full ynough of bloude. Theſe bee thoſe frowarde vngodlye ones, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> from their mothers wombe haue ſtrayed and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken lyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 58.</note> whoſe venom is as the poiſon of Serpents, who ſtil ymagine miſchief in their heartes, refuſing to heare the voice of the charmer (charme he neuer ſo wiſely) but wilfullye ſtop their cares bicauſe they wil not heare nor learne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12421:25"/>wyll of their heauenly Father.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman.</hi> 9.</note>‡ Theſe I ſaye be of them whom God hath ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp euen as he did Pharas, to bee as they haue bene, perſecutors of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to ſhew his power on them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the name of God myght be declared, who as he hath mercye on whom he will, ſo likewiſe thoſe whom he will he maketh harde hearted, euen as he doth theſe (if they repent not) on whom he wil ſhew his wrath, though he ſuffer them wyth long patience, being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veſſels of wrath ordeined to dampnation, yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende he will cut them from the earth &amp; wyth Pharao ouerwhelme and drown them in the ſorowfull Sea of perpetuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. The mercy ſhewed to them is but in vaine, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Ieſu Chriſte whereof they are wyſhed to bee partakers, is but caſt away vpon them, being as they are, playne contemners therof, ſhewing themſelues forſaken of God and left to themſelues, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not that which is holye to be giuen to ſuche dogges,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> for it is but as Pearles ſtrawed before ſwine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treade
<pb facs="tcp:12421:25"/>them vnder their feete and turne again to rent the giuers thereof, as they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready haue done and againe would doe if power &amp; beaſtly will were according. What otherwyſe therfore ſhall be done vnto theſe wilful ſtubborne ones ★ who being ignorant of Gods righteouſneſſe and going about to ſtabliſh their own,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 10.</note> and being diſobedient vnto the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God, if they will ſtil ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their vnfaithfulneſſe and be by no meanes conuerted vnto godwards, but euen according to the ſentence of God Almighty pronounced by Eſdras, dye in their vnfaithfulneſſe?
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 15.</note> ★ For the vngodly &amp; tranſgreſſors and ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnfaithful and obſtinate vnto the Lorde,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſaye.</hi> 1.</note> muſte altogither be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, yea deuoured with the ſworde.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eſdra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 7.</note> Againe Eſdras wylleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe which knowe not the lawe of God ſhoulde be taught, which much diſagreeth wyth ignoraunce to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as ſome of their affinitye haue taught, and thoſe (ſaith hee) that wyll not then fulfill the lawe of God and the kynges
<pb facs="tcp:12421:26"/>lawe; ſhall haue this iudgement with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delaye, loſſe of goodes, empriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and death,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eſdras.</hi> 6.</note> ★ then there ſhall be a beame taken from hys houſe and ſet vp, &amp; he ſhal be hanged theron. <note place="margin">4. <hi>Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 10</note> ★ And if Iehu did cauſe all the prieſtes of Baall to bee ſlaine and deſtroyed bicauſe they were the enimies of GOD, why then are theſe vyle Vypers and Romiſhe bloudſuckers,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 28.</note> theſe intollerable Diuils, vtter enimies both to God and their Prince, thus ſuffered to perſiſte in their euill, eſcaping ſo long the death which they ſo worthily haue deſerued, &amp; ſeing God wil haue his fierce wrath executed vpon hys enimies? Why are they ſtyll ſuffered thus to triumphe and proudly to make theyr vaunt and boaſt that the Prince hath no power to harme them?
<note place="margin">The brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Papiſtes. <hi>Abacuc.</hi> 1.</note> why are they I ſaye thus ſuffered to mocke their King &amp; laugh theyr Prince to ſcorne? Well, well, if God be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with pleaſed, then let it be ſtill as it is. But as certainely as God was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with king Saule forſparing of king Agag enimy to the children of God,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 15.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:12421:26"/>for reſeruing the Cattaile and beaſtes which he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be ſlaine, and Saule notwithſtanding doing therein as ſeemed beſt to hymſelfe, neglecting the commaundement of the hygheſt: euen ſo vndoubtedly is God nowe not pleaſed wyth the reſeruing of theſe ſo manifeſt enimies, who although they haue the ſhape of men, yet in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners more monſtrous and beaſtly than brute beaſtes in deede, who ſhould not thus long haue beene vnrewarded if there were not ſome either draw backs or claw backes, or both, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> looke ſmothe with theyr heades and ſting with their taile, bearing twoo faces in a hoode, whoſe power ouergoeth right and by whoſe meanes the lawe is torne in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſo that right iudgement cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede nor go forth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abacuc.</hi> 1.</note> but flattering Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are enimies to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel. Would God that ſuch as are infected and ſicke of that diſeaſe were diſpatched both fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> court &amp; countrey,
<note place="margin">Three chiefe poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to be noted.</note> for neuer ſhall truth tellers, bee thorowly welcome in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande tyll ſuch falſe flatterers be out of
<pb facs="tcp:12421:27"/>credit and eſtimation, neither ſhal that vggly Whore and ſhameleſſe ſtrompet of Babilon be cleane ouerthrowen, till ſuch hir loitering louers be brought to confuſion, nor yet the proude hearts of the arrogant Papiſts the vtter enimies to God and theyr Prince, bee mollified, meekened, and made humble and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, tyll Iudgement with iuſtice be ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned togither, the neglecting wherof is cauſe preſently that the boy preſumeth againſt the elder, and the vile perſon againſt the honorable. Wherefore mee think although there were no worde of God at all to inſtructe or moue vs, yet our conſciences would moue vs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder condigne puniſhement for ſuch ſo notorious greuous deteſtable tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours and offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dours as theſe ſtubborne rebels art, ★ who although they declare theyr owne ſinnes themſelues &amp; hyde them not, and that their wordes, works and counſels are againſt the Lorde our God and our Prince &amp; Soueraigne, yet are they wincked at and ſuffered. Yet notwithſtanding, as I doubt not but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12421:27"/>the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſty (to whom God graunt a long &amp; proſperous raigne to aduaunce his truth to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of his holy name, &amp; the vnſpeakable comfort of hys people committed to hit charge) is mindefull and well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the terrible threatening of God vpon Princes for not executing iuſtice, who hauing but deferred the ſame, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thorow hir cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; great mercy to bring them to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of God and their due obedience to hir Grace, yet lo, beyng but for thys cauſe prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ★ the innocent bloud of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled hath ſo long cryed vengeance vnto the Lorde vppon his enimyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apocal.</hi> 6.</note> and the ſoules of the righteous ſtill continually complaining, and the Lorde our God himſelfe hauing ſo long ſuffered, and holden backe hys hande, looking when the ſworde of iuſtice ſhould bee drawen by the Prince to whom hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executing of offendours, as well Idolatrers, murderers, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of whoredome, rebellious and enuious enimies of his truth, and ſeeth
<pb facs="tcp:12421:28"/>notwithſtanding his quarrel not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but the worthye extreme deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued puniſhement deferred, and iuſtice in his cauſe neglected,
<note place="margin">4. <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 15. The defer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice hath prouoked the wrath of God.</note> cannot, ★ bicauſe he wyll no longer ſuffer ſuche iniurye, but as a righteous iudge to reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hys owne cauſe doth nowe in his wrathfull indignation plentifully poure hys per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous plague of peſtilence vpon vs, in ſuch terrible wiſe, as that wee are glad to flye from our cities, miſlike our lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings, forſake our houſes, diſperſing our ſelues abroade in ſundrye places, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the meſſanger of God (death) dailye climing in at our windowes, is come into our houſes to deſtroy vs. Yea the Lorde as we ſee ★ conſumeth vs wyth the breath of hys wrathe euen as the wythered graſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 40.</note> and as he not long ſince, when wee were greater in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, tooke then from vs the fruite of the earth, or gaue ſo ſmall encreaſe therof, as that wee had not wherwyth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to feéde vpon: ſo nowe he hauing plentifully bleſſed the earth with ſtore, deſtroyeth now by death the people for
<pb facs="tcp:12421:28"/>whoſe ſakes he prouided &amp; appointed it.
<note place="margin">Two chief cauſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plague in London.</note> And the cauſes why that London ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allye is more ſharplyer viſited than any one place of Englande beſides (is) for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God being there moſt purelye and plentifullye preached and taught, is there leaſt followed. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe why, is, for that the enimies of God that haue bene ſuch ſhameleſſe ſhedders of innocent bloude &amp; pitileſſe perſecutors of him in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, haue bene there ſo long reſerued, where with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord (as well appeareth) is greuouſly offended and therefore hath layed the greater burden vpon vs. Wherfore we ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to much mercy is as well hurtfull to the offendours, as condigne puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is neceſſary,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieremy.</hi> 28. <hi>Deute.</hi> 13.18.</note> ★ who if they were cut away from vs, we ſhoulde be voide of euill, wherefore I would thoſe ſtumbling blockes were remoued, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of S. Paul,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gallath.</hi> 5.</note> I would God they were cut of from vs, which do diſquiet vs. And with Iob I ſay:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 24.</note> oh that all compaſſion vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ‡ for they diſpleaſe God &amp; hinder
<pb facs="tcp:12421:29"/>men from their ſaluation, God therfore for his great mercyſake graunt that the ſworde of Iuſtice no longer ruſte in the ſcabberde but that it may be put to the vſe that God hath apointed it, that ſuch may iuſtly receiue that which vniuſtlye they haue done vnto the clect ſeruants of God, and that as well the obſtinate Papiſtes as alſo the carnall Goſpellers may feele the wayght thereof, or elſe it wyll be ſtill the longer the worſe,
<note place="margin">To much mercy mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth good manners.</note> for to manifeſt it is at thys day in Englande, that the ouermuch mercy &amp; pitifulneſſe maketh a preſumpteous and careleſſe people, which if it be not the ſoner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, let vs aſſure our ſelues y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thys plague of peſtilence (wherewith wee haue lately periſhed ſo faſt) is but a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſorrowes and a declaration of a more heauy &amp; greuous vengeance of God to come vpon vs, which, if for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neglecting the punniſhing of ſinne and for not maintaining of Gods quarel be wilfully purchaſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woe, woe, woe will be vppon vs, for God will then ſo handle vs as he neuer did before,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezechiel.</hi> 5.</note> who
<pb facs="tcp:12421:29"/>hath plentye of plagues in ſtore, yea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuitic.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> euen readye hangyng ouer our heads. Wherefore good brethren let euery one of vs enter into himſelfe and well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the monſtrouſneſſe of our beaſtly behauiour that ſo ſhamefully aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, conſidering that where the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde bringeth forth the beſt wine the Lord doth keepe it and in due time wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it and preſerueth it daye and night from the enimy that he do it no harme,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 27.</note> but where the vineyarde yeldeth and bringeth forth bryers and thornes the Lorde will runne thorow it by warres and wil make the ſtrong cities deſolate and the habitation forſaken, &amp; God who made &amp; created the people, wyll not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour them. Beware I ſay therefore oh Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, be warned, be not tolong care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for it is manifeſt ynough vnleſſe we will be wilfull blinde,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 26.</note> that the hand of the Lord is lifted vp againſt vs, &amp; we haue felt the heauy burden therof vpon vs. The Lord graunt vs therfore grace &amp; ſpeedy amendement of our life, leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord in his wrath make of our Cities &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:12421:30"/>bleſſed famous &amp; fruitfull countrey an heape of broken ſtones,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 17.</note> as he did wyth Damaſcus or with the walled Citye of Aroer whereof hee threatned to make ſoldes of cattaill, and ſo we purchaſe to ourſelues ſorrow without hope of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort, from the which miſery that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God, in whoſe hands we are as the claye in the potters, may defende vs, let vs ſpeedely and continually in all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of heart, in weeping, faſting and praying in maner and forme follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, inuocate the name of God our heauenly father, to whom wyth the ſonne and the holye Ghoſt be all praiſe and glory, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            <p>(⁂)</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:30"/>
            <head>The Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H moſt puiſſant &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty king, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and of thy people Iſrael, who turneſt man to diſtruction and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine art gratious and mercifull, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer nowe from perill vs poore wretches that with vnfayned heartes call vppon thee, &amp; although our wickedneſſe paſt hath moſt highly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thee (oh Lord our God) and hath bene moſt grieuous in thy ſight, who therfore haſt layd thy heauy hande vpon vs, the ſmart wherof wee haue felte to our great diſcomfort, although not ſo ſharply as our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe well deſerued, yet nowe Lorde at the humble ſute of vs ſorowfull ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ceaſſe thy anger, withdrawe thy dreadfull hande, and let thy mercye quenche the flame of thy furye, looke downe vpon vs, beholde the miſerye of thy feeble flocke that are almoſt drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the dungeon of dolour, ſtop not thyne eares at the crying of our lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:12421:31"/>and mourning voyces, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, relieue vs, and ſuffer not the ſourges of ſorrowe to ouerwhelme vs, but rayſe thou vs vppe that are fallen, giue vs a Godlye conſideration of the wonderfull woorke of thy late wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indignation vppon vs by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe and diſtruction of the great number of oure Brethren, whome in thy ireful deſetued diſpleaſure by death thorowe Plague thou haſt taken from vs, that thereby wee being warned may henceforth eſchewe and auoyd the importable burthens of thy heauy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce that thou reſerueſt in ſtore for Sinners. Preſerue good Lorde the Queenes moſte excellente Maieſtye, and graunt hir to our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, a long and proſperous raigne, make hir zealous &amp; ſeruent in the tryall of thy truthe &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thy will and teſtament, and oh lord forgiue our enimies that haue ben perſecuters of thy people and ſelaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of thy truth and Goſpell, tourne their hearts if ſo it be thy heauenly wil, if not, (but that they bee of the number
<pb facs="tcp:12421:31"/>of thoſe whoſe hearts thou haſt harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bicauſe they ſhould not vnderſtand the myſteries contayned in thy holye word, nor the vnſpeakeable comfort co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the ſame) then ſuffer theyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord no longer to ſhaddow themſelues in ſecret corners priuyly to worke theyr perillous pretence, poyſoning thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wyth the peſtilent perſuaſion of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doctrine, but according to thy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſe, which is that the generation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ſhalbe without honour, ſo ſtand now vp Lord of hoſts and be no longer mercyful vnto thy enimies that of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious wickedneſſe reſiſting thy truth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſaline.</hi> 59.</note> do grenne as dogges at thy people, but thorow thy Godly motion, ſo moue the heart of our moſt gratious Queene, as Iehu, in the defence of thy Goſpell and people to drawe the ſworde committed to hir by thee, to cut away from the face of the earthe thoſe rebellious ennimies and ſworne aduerſaries agaynſte thee and thy Goſpell, to weede and roote out the rotten members that infect and poy ſon the body of the common welth, that
<pb facs="tcp:12421:32"/>then the noiſom number and remnant of the wicked being ſwept out with the beeſom of deſtruction, the flocke of thy folde thorow thy mighty aſſiſtance and gratious helpe and furtheraunce maye all the dayes of our lyfe be at defiaunce with Sathan, vtterly forſake, abhorre &amp; caſt of the patched lotheſome wycked weede of our olde Adam, and being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled and adorned wyth the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome garment and riche attyre of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, we may ſhine in all vertue, and be pleaſaunt and acceptable in thy ſight, to the praiſe and glory of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name and our eternall comforte. To thee oh God the Father, the Sonne, &amp; the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one immortal, inuiſible and euerliuing God, be all praiſe and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Giue God the prayſe. I. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12421:32"/>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, in <hi>Whitecroſſe</hi> ſtrete, by Henry <hi>Denham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno Domini. 1564.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
